So today's דף *daf* is כ"ה *Chaf-He*, 25. We pick up, we
back up a little bit, and we pick up at the bottom
of כ"ד *Chaf-Dalet* עמוד ב׳ *amud bet*. I just want to review
two important points that came up in the last few days when
I was gone and when it was יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom
Tov*. One is, I mean we started a new פרק *perek*. And
one of the important points of this new פרק *perek* is it
introduces this idea that you cannot catch fish or a wild animal
on יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov*. And that leads to an
important discussion in the ראשונים Rishonim *Rishonim*, which is why not? If
you can שחט shecht. *shecht* animals, why can't you catch? And that
again leads to this question of is it really true that you
can do any מלאכה melacha, *melacha* associated with preparation of food?
So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* basically says that the only real problem is
that you could have done it yesterday. You could have taken care
of it from beforehand.
Which basically the ראשונים Rishonim. *Rishonim* challenge. They say if something's really
related to food, direct food preparation, not indirect and preparatory, but direct
food preparation, even if you could have taken care of it beforehand,
you're allowed to do it on יום טוב Yom Tov, *Yom Tov*.
And anyway, it's not clear according to רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, would that
make it biblically forbidden? Because in theory you could have done it
beforehand, so the only things that you're biblically allowed to do are
things that you had no choice but to do on יום טוב
Yom Tov, *Yom Tov*? I mean, again, not no choice, but wouldn't
have been as good, like grinding spices wouldn't have been as good.
Anyway, that's רש"י Rashi *Rashi*'s approach, that basically gets rejected by the
ראשונים Rishonim *Rishonim*. There's enough evidence against that. So what's the difference?
So תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* quotes the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi*, the famous ירושלמי *Yerushalmi*
connecting him to פסח Pesach *Pesach* which we just left, that speaks
about ושמרתם את המצות *Ushmartem es hamatzos*, that connects the idea of
doing מלאכה melacha *melacha* juxtaposed to a פסוק *pasuk* about watching the
מצות *matzos* from becoming חמץ chametz *chametz*. When do you have to
watch the חמץ chametz *chametz* from becoming חמץ *chametz*? When you add
the flour to the water. So that the only מלאכות melachot *melachas*
that are allowed are מלאכות *melachas* that take place from the kneading,
לישה *lisha*,
K-N-E-A-D-I-N-G on. So obviously, now of course how does that correspond to
like meat? I mean what corresponds to the kneading of dough? I
mean okay, but somehow trapping this too is too early in the
process. The problem with that ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* is that there are מלאכות
*melachas* that are allowed. We've seen in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, we've
seen the discussion of בורר *borer* under certain circumstances when it's immediately
in the context of eating, grinding spices, all these things that normally
are in the מלאכה melacha? *melacha* category before you get to the
kneading of the dough, it's by the processing of the flour. So
that leads to a reconceptualization of what this idea is of מלישה
ואילך *milisha va'eilach*. And basically the way the רמב"ן Ramban's *Ramban* says
it, and again it sounds very clearly like he's talking at a
דאורייתא *de'oraisa*, at a biblical level, and this is a point I
made before, is that it's a distinction between, remember I mentioned to
you once before that the רמב"ן Ramban's *Ramban* says there are two
פסוקים *pesukim* that allow food preparation on יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom
Tov*. One is אך אשר יעשה לכל נפש *ach asher ye'aseh lechol
nefesh*, things that are done for the sake of food. And the
other is אך אשר יאכל לכל נפש *ach asher ye'achel lechol nefesh*,
יאכל *ye'achel*,
right, יאכל *ye'achel*, אך אשר יאכל
לכל נפש *ach asher ye'achel lechol nefesh*?
יעשה לכל נפש *ye'aseh lechol nefesh*? יאכל *ye'achel*? Anyway, יאכל לכל נפש
*ye'achel lechol nefesh*. Anyway. No, no, יעשה *ye'aseh*. זו לא עבודה לא
יעשה לכם *zo lo avodah lo ye'aseh lachem*. And the other is
that when it doesn't say that explicit allowance of יעשה לכל נפש
*ye'aseh lechol nefesh*, it says מלאכת עבודה *meleches avodah* as opposed to
by שבת Shabbat, *Shabbos* where it categorically prohibits מלאכה melacha *melacha*. So
the רמב"ן Ramban *Ramban* here focuses on the word מלאכת עבודה *meleches
avodah*. And he speaks about work that is done out in the
field לימים הרבה *leyamim harbeh* for like, you know, for many, many
days, like sort of a major processing as opposed to work that
is done like in the home for immediate eating of the food.
And that does not, it's not a categorical list of עבודות *avodos*.
You could have certain עבודות *avodos* like grinding, if what you're doing
is grinding your wheat and turning it into a flour, that's מלאכת
עבודה *meleches avodah*. If what you do is grinding your spices to
have freshly ground pepper or freshly ground spices, that's not מלאכת עבודה
*meleches avodah*, that's, that's a, you know, that's like a type of
a home-based, kitchen-based type of a thing that you do. And really
it doesn't become a categorical list of מלאכות *melachos*, but it's a
difference between the types of things you do in the context of
your home to prepare food, and the things you do out prior
to get before getting to the store, out in the field, large
scale, long term type of a thing. And therefore he says catching
animals, you know, is that prior type of מלאכה melacha *melacha*, it's
not the stuff you do in the immediate context of the making
of the food. And they did have fresh meat? Well, yeah, but
they don't go out and hunt that, I mean they are hunters,
but it's not the classic type of, you know, as the רמב"ן
*Ramban* says also, you wouldn't do it because again, if you're living
as a caveman and you're a hunter-gatherer you have no choice, but
if you're trying to live a domesticated life you want to have
the meat prepared, caught from days before so you can plan for
it, so you don't have to risk whether you're going to catch
the meat that
day. Believe me, my fishing abilities, I would not go out and
fish and assuming that that's the only, that that's what I'm going
to rely on for food that night, okay?
But you said fish ponds seem to be contained ponds, so there's
no fear that you're not going to catch?
Not so clear, depends, I mean no, if they were so contained
then, then it wouldn't be different than the animal case, the fish
case is not allowed because you might end up. Because it's less
caught than the animals, which are already caught. Anyway, this is the
basic, I'm not saying that you can't ask questions about this, but
this is the basic distinction. Thence with the ר"ן Ran basically gives
up and he sort of, he sort of buys into the רמב"ן's
type of a distinction, but he doesn't feel that it can really
work because he feels that if it were biblical, it would be
a distinction between between actual categories of מלאכה, melacha not the contexts
in which they took place. And therefore the ר"ן basically says it's
all rabbinic, that biblically you could do all this stuff. Biblically you
could go ahead and you could catch animals and harvest the wheat
and grind the wheat and it's all rabbinic, these distinctions. But most
of the ראשונים Rishonim, think it is biblical, but try to find
exactly what is the, you know, clear way of making the line.
The רמב"ן's conceptualization is probably the best for where do we find
that it's allowed and where do we find it's not allowed. And
this is the point I made before: things that are based like
the preparing of the home, going to the store and getting the
stuff and preparing at the home, this is also the carrying aspect,
as opposed to the stuff of like before it gets to the
store so to speak. Okay, so that's one issue I just wanted
to review. The other issue that now we're in the middle of,
the other very important issue, is the question about מלאכה melacha of
a non-Jew or if a non-Jew brings from
חוץ לתחום, chutz latchum, what is the story? Or if a non-Jew
does מלאכה? melacha Okay, so the גמרא Gemara, says like this. Let's,
so we're going to pick up with that right now. Okay, five
lines from the bottom. So there's obviously a מוקצה muktzeh issue if
the stuff was מחובר mechubar from before יום טוב Yom Tov and
it only got cut on יום טוב Yom Tov, or if it
only got caught on יום טוב, Yom Tov. it's a מוקצה muktzeh
issue. But now we're going to get to beyond even מוקצה muktzeh
concerns and let's take a look, five lines from the bottom. אמר
רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, says רב פפא, Rav Pappa, הלכתא, hilchata,
the הלכה halacha is, נכרי שהביא דורון לישראל ביום טוב, nochri sheheivi
doron leyisrael beyom tov, if a non-Jew brings a gift for a
Jew on יום טוב, Yom Tov. אם יש מאותו המין במחובר אסור,
im yesh me'oto hamin bimechubar assur,
if that type of a thing is, you
know, normally grows from the ground, is right now in a state
of being harvested, so there's a chance that it was harvested today
in your area, yeah, in your area, we just got through with
the whole discussion that ספק מוכן safek muchan is אסור, assur, so
then it is forbidden because it's מוקצה. muktzeh. Okay, you have to
assume that it was attached and it was harvested today and therefore
it's מוקצה. muktzeh. לערב נמי אסורין, le'erev nami assurin,
and in the evening, now in the evening there's no מוקצה muktzeh
concerns, right? It's the evening after
יום טוב. Yom Tov? So nevertheless it's still forbidden בכדי שיעשה, bichdei
sheye'aseh,
in the amount of time it would normally take to get this
done otherwise. Now of course how do you measure that, like let's
say the guy brings in, you know, 100 bushels of apples? Is
it how long it would take to get done with a crew
of 20 workers? Is it how long it would take to get
done if he was just just the actual מלאכה melacha of picking
the apple? Or is it the amount of time it would take
to bring the apples now back, you know, to the city and
where you are and where he's selling it? So that's an interesting
question of measuring בכדי שיעשה, bichdei sheye'aseh, but the point is you
cannot benefit from these apples until you wait past after יום טוב
Yom Tov the amount of time it would take in order for
them to be harvested. Now why, I'll get to in a minute,
but let's just understand that first point. And that's obviously not a
מוקצה muktzeh issue because it's
מוצאי יום טוב. motzaei Yom Tov. ואם אין מאותו המין במחובר, ve'im
ein me'oto hamin bimechubar,
now let's assume that, you know, apples are no longer on the
trees, it's post the apple season, so you know that the stuff
wasn't picked today. It's not a מוקצה muktzeh issue. So what would
the only concern be? The only, and it's יום טוב, Yom Tov,
it's not even a carrying issue. So the only issue would be
that maybe he brought it from חוץ לתחום. chutz latchum. Okay, so
תוך התחום מותר, toch hatchum mutar, if he brought it from within
the תחום tchum it's permissible, again what do you do exactly in
a case of ספק safek is not clear, but let's assume that
you can assume it's brought from within the תחום, tchum, it's okay.
חוץ לתחום, chutz latchum, top of כה עמוד א, kaf hei amud
aleph, if it was brought from outside of the תחום, tchum, then
אסור assur it is forbidden. You cannot benefit from it. How long?
בכדי שיעשה. bichdei sheye'aseh. But it's a similar type of an idea
we're seeing that even when מוקצה muktzeh is not an issue, if
the non-Jew did some violation in order to bring it to you,
it remains forbidden. והבא בשביל ישראל זה מותר לישראל אחר. ve'haba bishvil
yisrael zeh mutar leyisrael acher.
But if he brought it for one Jew, it's permissible for another
Jew. So what we have here is, aside from any מוקצה muktzeh
concerns, like it's מוצאי יום טוב motzaei Yom Tov in the first
case, or it wasn't even growing on the trees, there's still an
idea that you cannot benefit from what a non-Jew did for you
on יום טוב. Yom Tov, And you have to wait בכדי שיעשה
bichdei sheye'aseh and so on. Now why not? So there are two
approaches here. רש"י Rashi and then all the other ראשונים. What רש"י
Rashi, does is he ties this in to what we find in
שבת, Shabbat. which is basically called being נהנה nehaneh from the מלאכה
melacha of a non-Jew on שבת. Shabbat, So if a non-Jew lights
a candle for you, besides that there's a prohibition, I can't say
to him please light that candle, there's also... Okay, I mean we're
not going to talk about by how you use, how you ask,
like the maintenance people in a synagogue because that has to do
with צרכי רבים tzorchei rabbim and with indirection and hinting and so
on, but in a simple case, I can't say to a non-Jew,
"Please light that candle for me, please cook this food for me
on שבת," Shabbat, and if the non-Jew did it even without being
asked, even if he just went and he cooked it, but he
cooked it for you, not for him, not like he cooked it
for him and it was left over, he lit a candle for
him and his wife, no, he did it so he said, "I
wanted to cook you this nice dish for you here on שבת,
Shabbat. here it is," so the הלכה halacha is you're not allowed
to benefit from it. That's the concept of being נהנה neheneh from
מלאכת נכרי, melachet nochri, deriving benefit from the מלאכה melacha that a
non-Jew did for a Jew on שבת. Shabbat. So that is the
category that רש״י Rashi uses here to explain what is going on.
And he says it's the same therefore if he does מלאכה melacha
for you on יום טוב. Yom Tov? And that's why it's אסורין
assurin even—now why is it אסור assur after יום טוב? Yom Tov.
Okay, normally if a non-Jew lights a candle for me, does something
for me, I can benefit from it after שבת. Shabbat, So רש״י
Rashi says no, maybe as long as you are deriving benefit from
it—meaning as long as you are eating the food or using the
candle or eating the apples that were picked within the amount of
time, you know, and there hasn't been enough time to do it
after שבת, Shabbat then you're still deriving benefit, right? If it takes
an hour to get it done and I wait after שבת Shabbos
an hour and then I eat the fish or I eat the
apple, then I didn't really get benefit from the שבת Shabbos violation
because even had there not been a שבת Shabbat, violation, I could
be eating it now. But if I ate it within the hour
after שבת, Shabbos I derived benefit from the שבת Shabbos violation because
it allowed me to eat it immediately rather than having to wait
the time it would have taken. So for רש״י, Rashi, the reason
you have to wait בכדי שיעשו b'kdei she-ye'asu is so that it
should not be a way of deriving benefit from שבת Shabbat. violation,
which it will be in that time that it would normally have
taken it to be done because then you benefited from the fact
it was done on שבת. Shabbat That's how רש״י Rashi says what—one
minute—that's how רש״י Rashi says what's going on here. That's the problem,
deriving benefit.
No, on שבת Shabbat, it's obviously not okay, but it's even not
okay after שבת, Shabbat, and the same is true on יום טוב
Yom Tov, as well in the period of בכדי שיעשו. b'kdei she-ye'asu.
Now why therefore does רש״י Rashi say that therefore if it's אם
הבא בשביל ישראל זה מותר לישראל אחר? im ha-ba bishvil Yisrael zeh
mutar l'Yisrael acher?
Normally we say that if a non-Jew, if a non-Jew cooks a
fish for you or picks an apple for you on שבת, Shabbat,
no other Jew can use it. It was a מלאכה melacha, done
for a Jew on שבת, Shabbat. no Jew can derive benefit. So
רש״י Rashi says, well, okay, maybe that's in this special case of
תחום. techum. When the only problem was תחום techum and it's only
a rabbinic problem, then we were lenient and allowed another Jew to
derive benefit. This is more sharply said by רמב״ן, Ramban, and רמב״ן
Ramban says—and this is a whole fascinating issue about how do you
define what it means to—benefiting from מלאכה melacha on שבת. Shabbat, Let's
say the מלאכה melacha didn't produce anything, didn't create anything new. Now
what מלאכה melacha doesn't create anything new? So the biggest מלאכה melacha
that doesn't create anything new is carrying. If a non-Jew carries for
me on שבת, Shabbos can I derive benefit, or do you say
that—you say, "No, he did a מלאכה, melacha you're deriving benefit." No,
because the idea of not deriving benefit is that the שבת Shabbat.
violation created this new reality and I can't benefit from this new
reality. Carrying is not a new reality, it's not cooked food, it's
just here rather than there. Okay, so well, it's new for you,
that's true, well it's accessible to you. So there actually is a
debate about whether this idea of נהנה ממלאכת שבת neheneh mimelachet Shabbat
applies to carrying. But what's clear, this case of תחום techum is
even weaker than carrying, because תחום techum is, is that it's basically
like other people did have access to it, you know, and it
could actually be carried, it's just a question of like where you're
located and where it's located, and other Jews even had access to
it. So the רמב״ן Ramban says maybe that's why we go a
little bit more lenient here and we let another Jew get benefit,
especially because other Jews could have been within their תחום techum hypothetically.
So anyway, that's a special exception to this idea
of תחום. techum. But the basic point that רש״י Rashi says is,
this is the principle of מלאכת שבת, melachet Shabbat, being נהנה. neheneh.
One minute, that's רש״י. Rashi. תוספות Tosafot and רמב״ן Ramban and all
the other ראשונים and להלכה le-halacha reject that opinion, say yes, that
is a concern, but that's not what's going on here. Because that,
we never find that מלאכת שבת melachet Shabbat is אסור assur after
שבת. Shabbat And it goes ahead basically
if—well, if I, if a Jew let's say cooks an apple for
another Jew, so he you know so or whatever, or a Jew
just cooks an apple on שבת Shabbat, or picks an apple on
שבת, Shabbat. that apple, for him it might be אסור assur for
forever, whatever, but for other people, for the non-violator, not the... Person
who hasn't, the non-violator,
it's permissible immediately after שבת. Shabbat And they say this idea of
בכדי שיעשו bikhdei sheya'asu does not apply by normal מלאכות שבת. melachot
Shabbat. It applies specifically by מלאכה melacha done by a non-Jew. Why
does it apply specifically by מלאכה done by a non-Jew? Because מלאכה
done by a non-Jew is not just a problem that it was
a שבת Shabbat violation that created the fact that this thing now
is, I'm benefiting from a violation. If it was done by a
non-Jew, there's another concern. The concern
is
that it'll lead me to proactively
ask him to do it. Okay, if you let me benefit from
food cooked on שבת Shabbat by a Jew a minute after שבת
Shabbat is over, it would never in a million years, and תוספות
Tosafot say it's different because, you know, there's a lot of people
that, you know,
that don't operate within a context of any sense of הלכה halacha
and so on. So it's like, oh we'll just get this guy
who doesn't keep הלכה halacha anyway, we'll get him to do it.
I mean, that's a big problem. Like actually some פוסקים poskim say
that when it comes to doctors in the hospital, they דווקא davka
should not ask their non-observant Jewish doctor to take their shift on
שבת Shabbat because, you know, oh he doesn't keep שבת Shabbat, anyway.
No, אדרבה, adderaba, you know, if you're taking the shift, you'll be
more careful to only do the things you're allowed to do on
שבת, Shabbat, as opposed to if you give it to some, anyway,
that raises an interesting issue. But at least in the time of
the גמרא, Gemorah the assumption was that it would never occur to
me, just because you're letting me eat this picked apple a minute
after שבת, Shabbat that that's going to lead next שבת Shabbat for
me to ask my fellow Jew, who happened to accidentally pick it
today, that'll lead me next שבת Shabbat, to proactively ask him. Never
in a million years. But if you let me benefit from the
apples that a non-Jew picked, and you let me benefit from them
immediately after שבת, Shabbat? you know what I'm going to do next
שבת? Shabbat I'm going to make an arrangement for him to pick
them on שבת Shabbat so that I'll have those apples immediately מוצאי
שבת. motza'ei Shabbat. Like I had people ask me, can we get
a non-Jew, arrange for a non-Jew on the last day of פסח
Pesach? to go out to Dunkin' Donuts and buy up like all
of these bagels and donuts and that they'll be ready for us
at מעריב Ma'ariv on מוצאי פסח motza'ei Pesach that we'll be able
to eat from it right away? So that gets to issues of
owning חמץ and whose חמץ it is, but you know, that's the
thing you'd want to do. Have them do it on יום טוב,
Yom Tov have them do it on שבת Shabbat so it's available
immediately after. So they say because it's the non-Jew, it actually makes
it worse. Because it's the non-Jew, not only does it have the
מלאכת שבת melechet Shabbat aspect, that would be on שבת Shabbat, itself,
but that's why it goes and extends to after שבת, after יום
טוב, Yom Tov. בכדי שיעשו. bikhdei sheya'asu. So according to the תוספות
Tosafot and the רמב"ן and all the other ראשונים, בכדי שיעשו bikhdei
sheya'asu is only a concern by the מלאכה of a non-Jew. Okay,
and that's basically how they explain that what's going on here is
unique to that aspect. Yeah.
Mike, two questions. One they say is המחובר hamuchbar אסור assur or
whatever, can he be believed, say like, oh I know it's המחובר?
hamuchbar? Yeah, so that's not clear whether it's, whether, how, I mean
look, we learned before the issue of ספק. safek. So ספק מוכן
safek muchan it would be אסור assur presumably based on what we
said before. The other question is what about ספק חוץ לתחום? safek
chutz letchum? But anyway, I'm not getting into that, that is a
question. Yeah.
Like, you know, I think it also would depend on what it
is. Like let's say, you know, he's on his way back from,
you know, Virginia and he stops along somewhere else and he brought
me something you can only find there. Right. And so being, even
if it took, even if I say okay it was five hours,
whatever the drive is, but there's no way I'm going down there.
Right. I'm still benefiting from the fact that he did it. Right.
That is true. Well, no, but you could have had him do
it for you.
But he wasn't, you know what I mean? Like, you know.
Oh because he wasn't on his way back. Yeah. I mean there's
only some degree to certain degree that we can quantify it. I'll
just end by giving you one interesting נפקא מינה nafka mina by
the way, in addition to the בכדי שיעשו bikhdei sheya'asu question, which
is רש"י Rashi raises the question that Michael said. What about if
it's a two-day יום טוב? Yom Tov Let's say he does מלאכה
for me on day one of יום טוב. Yom Tov Can I
benefit from it on day two בכדי שיעשו? bikhdei sheya'asu? That's a
good question. So רש"י Rashi says yes I can. Why? It's the
whole type of the like of the ספיקא דיומא. sefeika deyoma. If
yesterday were חול, chol, he was allowed to do
the apple picking.
If yesterday were יום טוב, Yom Tov then today is חול chol
and then in hypothetically he could have picked the apples for me
in the last two hours since second day of יום טוב Yom
Tov, began. So therefore I can benefit it two hours into the
second day of יום טוב. Yom Tov. So תוספות Tosafot said, yes,
רש"י, Rashi I mean I'm paraphrasing, that works only according to you
because you think it's a, it's a conceptual issue of benefiting from
מלאכת יום טוב. melechet Yom Tov. So for you it's enough that
hypothetically he could have picked it today if today was חול. chol.
So therefore you're no longer benefiting from the violation because hypothetically it
could have been done either yesterday or today depending on which one
was יום טוב Yom Tov, and which one was חול. chol. But
as far as me, I don't care about hypothetic, I care about
practical. Is this going to lead you to get the non-Jew to
ask the non-Jew to do something for you? And you know what
the answer is? Yes, it will lead you. If you Let him
benefit from what he does on day one and eat from it
on day two, then that's going to lead me next יום טוב
Yom Tov to proactively have him do something for me on day
one so I can benefit from it on day two. So it's
all very nice hypothetically שקלא וטריא shakla v'tarya of the יומא, Yoma,
but in
practice בכדי שיעשו bichdei sheya'asu have to wait until after יום טוב
Yom Tov. when you really would have had to wait to have
done it if you were doing it yourself. Okay, so that's a
very important debate about that issue of a non-Jew doing מלאכה for
you and we פסקן pasken like תוספות's Tosafos interpretation of that issue.
Okay, yes,
Joseph?
Were you asking about the woman who works for you? So if
she cooks for herself can Joseph eat that too from... what? Joseph
has a woman who works for him. Yeah, so can if she's
cooking a meal...
Oh if she does it for herself, yeah, I mean, yeah, let's
put aside the issue of בישול עכו"ם, bishul akum, but this is
all if it's done for a Jew. If the non-Jew does it
for her, for him or herself, then you can benefit from it.
Okay. So now the גמרא Gemorah says like this. All right. So
that was a little bit of catch-up, now we're already behind. אמר
רבה בר רב הונא אמר רב הסוכר אמת המים מערב יום טוב
ולמחר השכים ומצא בה דגים מותרין. Amar Rabbah bar Rav Huna amar
Rav Hasocher amat hamayim me'erev Yom Tov ulmachar hishkim umatza bah dagim
mutarin. So you closed up your whatever your what's it called a
channel of anyway your
you know like with sluice gates what are those things called? Anyway
whatever it is your irrigation canal you closed it up so no
new water was getting in, it was a closed system, and you
did it ערב יום טוב erev Yom Tov and presumably in there
anything that's in there is considered already caught, it's small enough, we
had that discussion. So therefore and the next day you woke up
and you saw fish on יום טוב, Yom Tov, they're permissible because
they obviously were caught from ערב יום טוב erev Yom Tov and
they were מוכן. muchan. אמר רב חסדא מדברי רבינו נלמד Amar Rav
Chisda midivrei rabbeinu nilmad from the words of our rabbi meaning רב,
Rav, we can learn of our rabbi we can learn חיה שקיננה
בפרדס Chaya shekinina bepardes if a wild animal, a deer basically made
its nest you know in a garden like set up its little
home and the assumption here is also gave birth to a young
or had very young animals young children with it אינה צריכה זימון
eina tzericha zimmun
it does not need to be pre-designated, meaning two things: number one,
the animal is considered already caught because maybe it's a very young
animal, it's maybe even you know doesn't even really walk around so
much on its own, and because again it's sort of like accessible
and you're thinking about it, it's considered to be מוכן. muchan. So
it's both not a problem of צידה tzida and מוכן. muchan. Wait
a minute, the גמרא's Gemorah not done. אמר רב נחמן נפל חברא
בדרברבתא Amar Rav Nachman nefal chavraya bedarvavasa our friends, our colleagues, meaning
רב חסדא Rav Chisda who spoke about our rabbi you know our
rabbi רב, Rav, so he says our friend רב חסדא Rav Chisda
got himself into a debate of great ones because that meaning that's
not so obvious and we'll see in a minute that you can't
infer from the case of fish caught in a pond to animals
wild animals that are nesting. איכא דאמרי Ika d'amri some say אמר
רבה בר רב הונא מדברי רבינו נלמד. Amar Rabbah bar Rav Huna
midivrei rabbeinu nilmad. Some say it was רבה בר רב הונא Rabbah
bar Rav Huna said, it wasn't
רב חסדא Rav Chisda that said, it was רבה בר רב הונא
Rabbah bar Rav Huna himself said from the words of our rabbi
we
learn חיה שקיננה בפרדס אינה צריכה זימון. Chaya shekinina bepardes eina tzericha
zimmun. Okay, he was the one that said that that inferred from
the case of fish to the case of wild animals that nested.
אמר רב נחמן נפל בר חברא בדרברבתא. Amar Rav Nachman nefal bar
chavraya bedarvavasa. And then it was רב נחמן Rav Nachman who said
not our colleague but the son of our colleague, because this was
רבה בר רב הונא, Rabbah bar Rav Huna, so רב הונא Rav
Huna was their colleague. Anyway, he got himself mixed up into a
debate. What's the debate? So either way the question is you can't
really infer from the fish to the wild animal. התם לא קא
עביד מעשה. Hatam lo ka avid ma'aseh. There in the case for
the wild animals you didn't do anything, they just took up nesting
on their own. So what's there to indicate that you're planning even
if they're considered already caught and they're not wild or whatever and
they don't need being caught, what makes them not מוקצה? mukhtzah? They
just did it on their own. There's nothing that reflects the reality
that you're planning on using them. It's just something that happened out
in the wild. הכא Hacha and I mean even if the פרדס
pardes is your back even if it's your garden in your backyard
there's nothing that designated it that you were planning on using it.
הכא קא עביד מעשה. Hacha ka avid ma'aseh. Here you did something,
you closed the sluice gates, you actually did something that caught the
fish. Okay. ולא בעי זימון? V'lo ba'ei zimmun? Now the גמרא Gemorah
says,
so first of all I don't think that it's necessarily so clear,
you know hypothetically you could distinguish. And now the גמרא's Gemara going
to say it's not only hypothetical, I'm going to show you evidence
that you that you need זימון, zimmun, you need designation in this
case of the wild animal. דהתניא Dehatanya we taught in a ברייתא
braita חיה שקיננה בפרדס צריכה לזמן Chaya shekinina bepardes tzericha l'zamen a
wild animal sort of took up lodging in a garden,
you have to designate, you have to verbally say I plan on
using that baby deer tomorrow on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Okay? וציפור
דרור צריך לקשור בכנפיה V'tzippor dror tzarich likshor bichnafeha and a ציפור
דרור tzippor dror which is like
a... now if that's an animal that you actually did designate from
the day before although
a דרור... dror... But that would be a bird that you caught
and designated from the day before, nevertheless you need to tie up
its wings, not not to do the act of זימון, zimmun, but
כדי שלא תתחלף kedei shelo titchalef so you don't get confused which
is the bird you designated and which was the one you did
not. Okay. באמה be'imah and you shouldn't confuse it with its mother,
because apparently Rashi says this is a species of birds that the
young are almost the same size as the mother. So even though
it's a little nest and you say, oh, I know I'm going
to use the chick, no, it'll be confused and you'd have to
tie up its wings. וזו עדות שהעידו מפי שמעיה ואבטליון v'zu eidut
she-heidu mipi Shmaya v'Abtalyon and this actually the testimony that goes all
the way back to שמעיה ואבטליון, Shmaya v'Abtalyon, the rabbis of Hillel
and Shammai. So תיובתא. tiyufta. The Gemara says, all right, that's a
contradiction. That shows you that in this case of the wild animal,
when you didn't do an act, you need לזמן. lezamen.
So now the Gemara says, ומי בעי זימון? u-mi ba'ei zimmun? One
so now the Gemara switches gears. Wait a minute, is that really
true? You do do you really need זימון zimmun in this case
of the wild animal? דהתניא d'hatanya we learned a Braisa, אמר רבי
שמעון בן אלעזר amar Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar says רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, מודי בית שמאי ובית הלל על שזימנם
בתוך הקן ומצא לפני הקן שאסורין. modei Beit Shammai u-Veit Hillel al
she-zimnam betoch haken u-matza lifnei haken she-asurin. You might remember that going
back to the first perek, that the the ones the birds you
designated inside of the nest and then you found birds outside of
the nest they're forbidden because you have to be afraid these aren't
the same ones that you designated. במה דברים אמורים bameh devarim amurim
when is this true? ביוני שובך ויוני עלייה b'yonei shovach v'yonei aliyah
this is true about birds of the of the coop and birds
of the of the loft וצפרים שקיננו בטפיחים ובבירה v'tzipparim she-kinenu b'tapichim
u'v'birah and birds that have taken up nest in like the little
crevices in the wall. אבל aval but meaning normally birds that are
normal wild birds. Okay, so those are ones that need זימון zimmun
and these might not be the ones that you were מזמן mezamen
because normally they're not understood to be ones that normally you're planning
on using. אבל aval but אווזים ותרנגולים avazin v'tarnigolin if you're a
farmer and you've got ducks and chickens ויוני הרדיסיות v'yonei hordisiyot and
you know Herodian pigeons which are normal ones that were kept for
breeding and ones that you would regularly use like if you're hungry
you'll just go out to your chicken your pigeon coop and shecht
the pigeon for tonight. וחיה שקיננה בפרדס v'chayah she-kinena b'pardes so in
addition to those animals you normally draw on for your meals also
a wild animal a deer let's say that took up lodging in
your in your garden, מותרין muttarin they're permissible without any זימון. zimmun.
So here we see so everything worked out makes sense. Things you
normally use for eating as opposed to things that you maybe even
some things you're even raising but you don't normally use for eating
you know which do need זימון zimmun which do not, but the
wild animal that took up nesting is a contradiction. One Braisa said
according to שמעיה ואבטליון Shmaya v'Abtalyon it needs זימון zimmun and this
Braisa says that that wild animal does not need זימון. zimmun. Wait
a minute.
ואין צריכין זימון v'ein tzerichin zimmun וציפור דרור צריכה לקשור בכנפיה כדי
שלא תתחלף באמה v'tzippor d'ror tzaricha likshor bichnafeha kedei shelo titchalef be'imah
that's what we said before, this type of bird the ציפור דרור
tzippor d'ror even if you were מזמנה mezamna it you need to
bind up its wings so you don't confuse it with its
mother. ובקשורים ובמנועים u'vikshurim u'vimnu'im and things by the way that have
bound up birds and birds that have obviously been disturbed and moved
בבורות ובשיחין ובשיחין ובמערות b'vorot u-v'shichin u-v'shichin u-v'mearot whether you find them
in wells and in houses or in other types of like שיחין
shichin no no
שיחין ומערות shichin u-mearot is a goes with בור ושיח bor v'shiach
is a is a what do you call it it's a it's
a type of a well, it's a well with a yeah בור
ושיח bor v'shiach go together and in the
and in caves מותרין muttarin they are permissible. ובילאנות u'v'ilanot
meaning ואילנות v'ilanot אסורין asurin but so all these things even if
you were מזמן mezamen them they're permissible if they are in all
these various locales but they're forbidden if they're in trees. Why? Even
though you were מזמן mezamen them, שמא יעלה ויתלוש shema ya'aleh v'yitlos
because how are you supposed to get access to them? And you'll
say oh just pick it off of the branch. We don't let
you pick it off of the branch because we're afraid you'll come
to climb up and to pull off branches and to use the
tree. So that's another point in addition to being מזמן mezamen them
you have to you can't get the you can't get access to
them if they're in trees.
והקשורים והמנועים v'hakshurim v'hamnu'im now if they are bound birds or they've
obviously somehow been moved, I don't know how you would see that
but somehow you see that they've been handled by people and they're
not yours. So all that was your bird you don't some of
them that are the certain ones you don't need to be מזמן
mezamen others you need to be מזמן mezamen and you need to
and but you need to sort of like tag and then you
know and they have to be in certain places that you can
have access to them. But if they're ones that have been tagged
by other people then בכל מקום אסור משום גזל bechol makom asur
mishum gezel then obviously then forget Yom Tov you can't anyway take
them, clearly they're somebody else's and it's forbidden because of גזל. gezel.
Okay, that was I don't know pretty pretty obvious but has to
do with issues of קנינים kinyanim and anyway not related to Yom
Tov. So anyway we have our problem here about wild birds that
took up nesting in a garden. Do they need זימון zimmun or
not?
So אמר רב נחמן לא קשיא. amar Rav Nachman lo kashya. get
away, that doesn't need זימון. zimun. The mother deer, the deer that
can run away, that needs זימון. zimun. So because, you know, it's
not going to be easy to catch it. So the Gemara says:
אמא בזימון סגי לה? Ima bezimun sagi lah? I don't get it,
says the Gemara, the mother, זימון zimun isn't enough, it's not just
an idea of מוקצה. muktzeh. צידה מעליא בעיא, Tzeida me'alya ba'ya, right?
It's not in any cage, you would actually have to trap the
mother. So there's always two issues. So we're assuming all these animals
are already trapped and the only question is זימון. zimun. But the
Gemara says: How is this wild deer in your garden already trapped?
Maybe the baby is effectively trapped, but not the mother. So you
can't say the mother is the one that needs זימון, zimun, the
mother is אסור assur completely, you can't trap it.
You mean it was because it set up its nest in a
domesticated area, it was up until that קשיא kasha being treated I
thought as if it were trapped of its own as it were.
No, because, well, for that's what the Gemara is revealing is that
even if it's in a domesticated area, like if you have a
deer walking in your backyard, but the right,
but the assumption here what the Gemara is revealing is that the
mother deer is not going to wait around to be trapped just
because she set up a nest.
But up until that
קשיא, kasha, you might have thought that, right?
This reveals that the קנין kinyan of her חצר chatzer only works
for the child who cannot easily escape. That is correct. The Gemara
did not make that clear until this point. I mean רש"י did,
but the Gemara didn't. So אלא אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק אידי
ואידי בדידה. Ella amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak idi ve'idi bedida. Fine,
we're talking in both cases about the child, and in both cases,
you know, it's already considered trapped, it's not going to easily get
away. So do you need זימון zimun or not? But here's the
difference: הא בגינה סמוכה לעיר הא בגינה שאינה סמוכה. Ha begina smucha
le'ir ha begina she'eina smucha. The question is where is this garden?
Is it basically in your backyard or is the garden out in
some, you know, in your apple orchard somewhere out at the edges
of the city? So again, now it's a question of effectively it's
trapped, if you wanted to you could capture it without any problem,
but does it need זימון? zimun? So if it's a baby deer
in your backyard, it doesn't need any act. You can assume you're
going to plug, it's great, they'll have some venison for יום טוב,
Yom Tov and you don't need any words and you don't need
anything, it's considered to be in your mind, presumably you know about
it, that you would plan to use it, whereas if it's not
so local, then it would need זימון. zimun. Yes.
He's also trying to understand from the beginning, when you say it's
set up its nest in a domesticated area, it's okay for this,
but how is that different than the דגים dagim and the ביברין?
bevarin? Like if it's a big one or
if it's a big
one?
Like basically, like
you know, you put in your net, you're definitely going to get
something.
Right, yeah, effectively, yeah, I mean that you have to assume something
like that. Right, true.
But Rabbi,
why does it have to be the assumption is the baby? Doesn't
this last piece here say: listen, if it's in the פרדס, pardes,
right? Depends, is the פרדס pardes סמוכה לעיר? smucha le'ir?
No, but that would not affect the issue about what do you
call it, about צידה מעליא בעיא. tzeida me'alya ba'ya. He's effectively trapped
depending upon how the garden's set up.
I don't see how that could at all be relevant to that,
and our basic issue is to explain the זימון zimun question. So
being local addresses the issue of זימון, zimun, it does not address
the question about how much trapping it needs. Right, being local or
not local responds to צידה מעליא בעיא.
tzeida me'alya ba'ya.
Yeah, exactly. So but צידה מעליא בעיא tzeida me'alya ba'ya therefore you're
right, we're not talking about the mother. The Gemara is shocked at
the suggestion of the mother. So the basic answer is forget the
mother, you're right, it's just a מוקצה muktzeh issue, it's just about
the child. The fact that it says בדידה bedida and not ב,
you notice the word: הא ב הא באמא. It doesn't say הא
בולד הא באמא Ha bevlad ha be'ima or הא, you know. ב
means it's always been assuming the subject has been the child. For
you, that was a חידוש, chiddush, but the Gemara has been assuming
that the subject has been the child. Okay, next משנה. mishna. בהמה
מסוכנת לא ישחוט אלא אם כן יש שהות ביום לאכול ממנה כזית
צלי. Behema mesukenet lo yishchot ella im ken yesh shahut bayom leechol
mimena kezayit tzli. So here again we get the issue of doing
certain מלאכות on יום טוב Yom Tov, that are allowed for לצורך
אוכל נפש, letzorech ochel nefesh, but in your mind, you're also thinking
about after יום טוב. Yom Tov, So like שחיטה shechting an animal
because you want to eat just a little bit and the rest
of the meat is going to be for after יום טוב, Yom
Tov or filling up a whole pot and you're only going to
eat a little bit, but you have the rest of it for
after יום טוב. Yom Tov. So here you have an animal that's
about to drop dead out of old age. Now it's not a
טרפה, treifa, for if a טרפה treifa שחיטה shechting it wouldn't help,
but it's about to drop dead out of old age. If you
wait till after יום טוב Yom Tov. and it drops dead, it's
a נבלה, nevela, right? It did not have a kosher שחיטה. shechita.
So you want to שחיטה shecht it on יום טוב, Yom Tov.
not so much because you need an extra hamburger on יום טוב,
Yom Tov but because you don't want to waste the entire animal,
and if you שחיטה shecht it on יום טוב and you שחיטה
shecht it before it dies, it won't be, it'll be kosher. So
it says you cannot שחיטה shecht it unless you have time, the
amount of time to eat at least one roasted כזית kezayit on
יום טוב. So then in theory, we could say it was being
done for the sake of יום טוב. Now it's interesting, it doesn't
say you have to actually go ahead and roast that כזית kezayit
and that has to be your intent is to
eat, right, that also also... as long as you're doing a little
bit for יום טוב. How much can it be like a trick?
How much can it be, oh I'll take a little taste now
and that counts even though most of it is for after יום
טוב and how much does it have to really be that you
really do want to be eating from this stew right now? So
the משנה Mishnah here doesn't say that אלא אם כן יאכל ממנו
כזית צלי. ela im kein yochal mimenu kezayis tzaluy. It also only
says only as long as it's theoretically you could eat a כזית,
kezayis, that would be enough. רבי עקיבא אומר אפילו כזית חי מבית
טביחתה. Rebbi Akiva omer afilu kezayis chai mibeis tveichasa. Even a raw
כזית kezayis of meat. In theory you could eat raw meat. So
even a raw כזית kezayis of meat from the place it was
שחט. shecht You just grab from the neck area because that's already
where it's splayed and it's easy to get access. So you just
need a few seconds to grab a כזית kezayis from the neck.
Well that's the issue about salting. If
the blood doesn't come out and go back in it doesn't need
salting. That's the same reason why roasting meat doesn't have to get
all the blood out. שחטה בשדה לא יביאנה במוטות ובמוטה אבל מביא
בידו אברים אברים. shachata basadeh lo yivenah bimotos u'bimotah aval meivi biyado
evarim evarim.
If you did שחט shecht this or any animal out in the
field you cannot bring it in unlike these beams like sort of
those images of the spies bringing back the grapes. You can't bring
it back on these crossbeams or whatever these carrying beams because that
makes it feel like a weekday like you're bringing a whole animal
slaughtered animal from the market to the marketplace or something. But you
can bring in sections and bring back sections at a time in
your hands. Even though it's more טרחא tircha but it's less עובדא
דחול. uvda d'chol. Okay, Dov you had a question?
What I didn't understand about this משנה Mishnah ever was this הוה
אמינא hava amina that you can eat from a מסוכנת mesukenes and
here you're talking לכתחילה lechatchila the assumption was that you're looking at
a טריפה treifa of it.
No, so that's what I said that
טריפה treifa is different than מסוכנת. mesukenes. מסוכנת mesukenes means that it
might die out of old age or disease but טריפה treifa specifically
is that it has like a puncture. So you could have an
animal that is about to die that is not a טריפה. treifa.
Okay, which is also the גמרא Gemara distinguishes between somebody who kills
a person who's a טריפה treifa and somebody who kills
and right and a person who's a גוסס. goses. A גוסס goses
person who's about to die but he's not in the category of
a טריפה. treifa. Okay. So אמר רמי בר אבא הפשט וניתוח בעולה
והוא הדין לקצבים. Amar Rami Bar Abba hefsheit venituach be'olah vehu hadin
laktzavim.
So when the תורה Torah speaks about bringing a קרבן עולה korban
olah it says הפשיט את העולה ונתח אותה לנתחיה.
hiphshit es ha'olah ve'nitach
osah linetacheha.
So okay, you should flay it and cut it into its
members and chop it into its parts. So the תורה Torah says
it by an עולה olah but the same is true about butchers
that after you שחט shecht you need to flay it and chop
it into its parts. What does that tell you?
מכאן למדה תורה דרך ארץ שלא יאכל אדם בשר קודם הפשט וניתוח.
mikan limdah Torah derech eretz shelo yochal adam basar kodem hefsheit venituach.
You should not eat meat before you've had a chance to flay
it and to chop it up. You shouldn't be so ravenous that
as soon as an animal
is שחט shecht. the גמרא Gemara is going to ask you stuff
it in your mouth. Now this seems to be simply saying just
an issue about דרך ארץ. derech eretz. Don't be ravenous wait for
us to flay and to chop it up and so on. But
the גמרא Gemara is going to think that maybe he's even making
a הלכה halacha point, not just a דרך ארץ derech eretz point.
So the גמרא Gemara says מאי קא משמע לן? mai ka mashma
lan? What's the point of this? אילימא לאפוקי מדרב הונא ilaima lapokei
mid'Rav Huna to reject the position of רב הונא. Rav Huna. דאמר
רב הונא d'amar Rav Huna רב הונא Rav Huna says the following:
בהמה בחייה בחזקת איסור
עומדת עד שיודע לך במה
נשחטה. beheimah bechayeha bechezkas issur omedes ad sheyivada lecha bemani shechitah. A
walking around living breathing animal is בחזקת איסור bechezkas issur even a
cow because it's not שחט. shecht
Unless you know that it was שחט shecht properly. Now what's the
point of saying that? It's not just you have to שחט shecht
an animal. It's saying if you have a doubt whether the שחיטה
shechitah was done properly. You don't know if there was a nick
in the knife and whether the nick in the knife came before
or after the שחיטה. shechitah. He's telling you well it had a
חזקת איסור. chezkas issur. Before it was שחט shecht it had a
label of being אסור. assur. And you cannot remove that status of
חזקת איסור chezkas issur unless you definitely know that it was שחט
shecht properly. So if it is a different איסור, issur, so תוספות
Tosafos creates an איסור issur rather than אבר מן החי. eiver min
hachai. So it says that's a different איסור issur than not שחט
shecht it properly which is נבילה. neveilah. So תוספות okay he creates
this איסור issur called אינו זבוח. eino zavuach. Not שחט shecht which
applies whether it's alive or dead based on the מצוות עשה mitzvas
aseh וזבחת ואכלת. ve'zavachta ve'achalta. Okay so he says it has a
status of אסור חזקת איסור assur chezkas issur and therefore any doubt
about the שחיטה shechitah it remains אסור. assur. You need to definitely
know the שחיטה shechitah was done correctly. That's point number one. נשחטה
nishechata
now let's say you know the שחיטה shechitah was done correctly, the
knife was done was perfect, you watched it it was a perfectly
executed שחיטה. shechitah. Then בחזקת היתר עומדת. bechezkas heter omedes. It has
a presumption of being מותר mutar עד שיודע לך במה נטרפה. ad
sheyivada lecha bemah nitreifah.
And until you know for sure that there was a טריפה treifa
which means we assume animals are not a טריפה. treifa. You שחט
shecht an animal it has a חזקת היתר chezkas heter and therefore
you do not have to now verify that there are absolutely no
טריפות treifos in the animal. You do not now have to check
every single organ and make sure that there are no
טריפות. treifos. Any doubt is ignored unless you know for certain that
it actually is a טרפה. treifa. So here it works the opposite.
Any doubt is ignored unless you know for certain it is a
טרפה. treifa. Now by the way that's not exactly the הלכה. halacha.
The הלכה halacha distinguishes between two types of doubt. A מיעוט המצוי
mi'ut hamatzui and a מיעוט שאינו מצוי. mi'ut she'eino matzui. A מיעוט
שאינו מצוי mi'ut she'eino matzui is normally defined as let's say less
than 5% occurrence, we don't have to be concerned with it at
all. But once something happens 5% or more of the time, then
the assumption is that if it's possible to check, we need to
check. And that's why we check like the lungs, because problems in
the lungs happen 5% or more of the time, so since it's
available to us to check, we need to check. But let's say
you lost the lungs. You שחטed shecht the cow and somehow the
cat made off with the lungs. The הלכה halacha would be מותר.
mutter. It has a חזקת היתר. chezkas heter. So even if you've
got some doubt, if you don't know, if it's possible to check
maybe you do check, but if it's not possible, it's מותר mutter
until you know for sure that it's אסור. assur. That's what Rav
Huna says, we פסק pasken that way. So maybe you're coming to
reject Rav Huna. You're saying, don't eat from it until you flay
it and dismember it. Maybe the reason you're demanding flaying and dismemberment
is to give us a chance to do what? To say we
have to check it for טרפות treifas before we're going to let
you eat from it. The גמרא Gemara says ואנן תנן מתניתין כרב
הונא. ve'anan tenan matnisin ke-Rav Huna. Our משנה Mishnah supports Rav Huna
that הלכהally halachic it's allowed.
דתנן, De-tenan, Rabbi Akiva אומר, omer, אפילו כזית חי מבית טביחתו. afilu
kezayis chai mibeis tevichaso. You can even have a raw כזית kezayis
of meat from the place it was שחטed. shecht So you see
you don't have to הלכהally halachic wait to check for טרפות. treifas.
So the גמרא Gemara says מאי לאו מבית טביחתו ממש? mai lav
mibeis tevichaso mamash? Does it not literally mean from the place in
the neck where it was
שחטed? shecht לא ממקום שטובחת אכילתה. Lo, mimakom shetovachas achilasah. No, what
it means is from the place where the food gets ground and
gets digested, meaning from the stomach meat, which is very bizarre. Why
would Rabbi Akiva say as long as you can eat a כזית
kezayis of the stomach meat? So the גמרא Gemara says רש"י says
because maybe that's like considered easily digestible or something. I don't know,
it's very bizarre. Something you would be prepared to eat raw, like
I won't eat meat raw unless we're talking about the organ meat.
Then I'll eat it raw, I suppose. The גמרא Gemara says ותני
רב חייא, ve-tanei Rabbi Chiya, but that's not true because Rabbi Chiya
says in the, it has a ברייתא, braisa, מקום טביחתה ממש, makom
tevichasah mamash, that literally Rabbi Akiva means the place where it was
שחטed, the neck meat. So anyway you see that you do not
הלכהally halachic nobody disagrees that you need to dismember it and check.
We all agree you don't need to, you can eat from it
before you've checked for טרפות. treifas. So therefore what is the point
of saying that you need to flay it and dismember it? אלא,
Ella, Rami bar Chama, not Rami bar Chama, who is it? Rabbi
bar Abba, אורחות דארעא orchis de-aretz קמשמע לן, kamashma lan, like you
said from the outset, he wasn't telling us הלכה. halacha. You're right,
הלכהally halachic it's מותר mutter even before you've checked it. He was
just telling us basic דרך ארץ. derech eretz. Don't be so ravenous
to tear from the meat before it's been flayed and dismembered. כדתניא,
Kid-tanya, like we taught in the ברייתא, braisa,
לא יאכל אדם שום ובצל מראשו אלא מעליו. lo yochal adam shum
ubatzal meroshu ella me'alav. Do not eat a garlic or an onion
from the top of it, meaning I guess we would call it
the bottom of it, but rather from the place where the leaves
grow out, from what we would call the top. Anyway somehow if
you eat from towards the root of it, that's like oh my
god you're so ravenous you can't even wait to eat it in
a normal way. Again I don't know exactly why that shows that
you're ravenous, maybe because you don't even want to bother to have
to pick the leaves. ואם אכל הרי זה רעבתן. Ve-im achal harei
ze ra'avtan. And if you eat that way you're showing yourself to
be ravenous. The whole point of bringing this in is to show
that sometimes Rabbinic literature addresses itself not to הלכה halachic questions but
just not to act in ways that are ravenous. And that was
the point of the teaching of the raw meat as well. כיוצא
בו, Ke-yotzei bo, similarly, לא ישתה אדם כוסו בבת אחת. lo yishkeh
adam koso bevas achas. Don't drink up your entire glass in one
gulp, presumably talking about wine. ואם שתה הרי זה גרגרן. Ve-im shasah
harei ze gargran. And if you did then you are a also
like ravenous or a glutton or whatever the liquid equivalent is of
a glutton.
What about the פסח? Oh god the whole thing in one or
no? Well they say you're supposed to have like a רוב כוס,
rov kos, but not the whole glass. Right. It's not the whole
thing,
separate thing. Sometimes you know you're really like you said oh my
god I didn't realize how dehydrated I was because once you start
drinking you don't... oh I was just... so anyway תנו רבנן, tanu
rabanan, our rabbis taught: השותה כוסו בבת אחת הרי זה גרגרן. hashoseh
koso bevas achas harei ze gargran. If you drink it all down
in one gulp you're ravenous. שנים, Shenayim, in two gulps, דרך ארץ.
derech eretz. That's like the normal way. Okay שלשה, sheloshah, if you
take it so sip it so daintily and slowly,
three separate drinks, מגסי הרוח, migasay haruach, then you're being very haughty.
All right. Anyway you see though that we bother teaching you about
how to act in ways that are just civility. Civility, right. ואמר
רבי בר אבא, Va-amar Rabbi bar Abba, חצובה מקטע רגליהן דרשיעייא. chatzuva
mekate'a ragleihen de-rashi'aya. So the חצובה, chatzuva, which is basically a type
of a grass that grows straight down and it was used, the
גמרא says by יהושע, Yehoshua, to show the boundaries. of the land
that you have this grass that grows straight and it clearly demarcates
the boundaries, that cuts the legs out from under the wicked people.
What does that mean? So רש״י Rashi says it's more symbolic that
you see there's this grass that grows straight and stays exactly in
its boundary and if you're the type of person that's coveting and
stealing land that's not yours, you should have learned a lesson from
the grass. The מהרש״א Maharsha says it's better than learning a lesson.
What you're going to do is you want your neighbor's field, you
mow down the grass, you stake a claim in his field and
you say it's yours, and then when you start digging up the
land underneath, you see the roots of this grass and of this
weed, and that proves that you stole his land. So it undercuts
your legs because this grass basically undercuts his legs,
shows that this person was stealing. נטיעה מקטעה רגליהון דכסויא ודבעלי נדות.
Neteia mekatea ragleihen dekasvaya ud'baalei niddot. Now you'll see why we're mentioning
this because of the next line. נטיעה מקטעה רגליהון דכסויא ודבעלי נדות.
Neteia mekatea ragleihen dekasvaya ud'baalei niddot.
The plantings, which means the fact that you have to wait three
years before you can eat from the fruit of a tree because
of ערלה. Orlah. So you invest all of this time and effort
and you need a lot, lot of patience and self-restraint.
And that's what the תורה Torah tells you by ערלה. Orlah. That
should be a lesson for the butchers and for the בעלי נדות.
baalei niddot. So the butchers are the people that as we've been
talking about
that will eat the meat before they've had a chance to check
for טריפה. treifa. Now even though that technically you don't have to
check for טריפה, treifa, you can assume it's מותר, mutar, but nevertheless,
the proper thing to do is who wants to find out a
week later that because you rushed to eat the meat and you
didn't check, it winds up you ate טריפה? treifa? So you should
learn a certain amount of restraint and patience from the principle of
ערלה Orlah even if technically you're allowed to eat from the meat
before you've flayed and dismembered and checked it. And similarly certainly the
case of
בעלי נדות, baalei niddot, men that cannot wait to have sex with
their wives before they've had a chance to go to the מקוה,
mikvah, they should learn a lesson from how much patience it takes
in the case of ערלה. Orlah. So sometimes you need a little
patience before you can have some of the pleasures in life. טורמוסא.
Tormusa. So anyway that was the tie-in. טורמוסא מקטע רגליהון דשנאיהון דישראל.
Tormusa mekatea ragleihen desoneihen deYisrael. Now טורמוסא, Tormusa, which is a type
of a bean that requires cooking seven times before it could be
eaten, that undercuts the legs of the enemies of the Jews, which
means the Jews. שנאמר, Shene'emar, as the verse says, ויסיפו בני ישראל
לעשות הרע בעיני ה׳, Vayosifu b'nei Yisrael la'asot hara b'einei Hashem, they
continued to do evil in the eyes of God, ויעבדו את הבעלים,
vayavdu et ha-Ba'alim, they worshiped the foreign gods, ואת העשתרות, v'et ha-Ashtarot,
count the number of different foreign gods: בעלים Ba'alim one, עשתרות Ashtarot
two, ואת אלהי ארם v'et elohei Aram three, ואת אלהי צידון v'et
elohei Tzidon four, ואת אלהי מואב v'et elohei Moav five, ואת אלהי
בני עמון v'et elohei b'nei Amon six, ואת אלהי פלשתים v'et elohei
Plishtim seven. Now this טורמוסא Tormusa requires seven cookings before it could
get ready, before it could be eaten.
ואת ה׳ עזבו ולא עבדוהו, v'et Hashem azvu v'lo avaduhu, and they
abandoned God and didn't worship Him. ממה שנאמר, Mimah shene'emar, ואת ה׳
עזבו, v'et Hashem azvu, once it says they abandoned God, איני יודע
שלא עבדוהו, eini yode'a shelo avaduhu, I don't know that they didn't
worship Him? ומה תלמוד לומר ולא עבדוהו, u'mah talmud lomar v'lo avaduhu,
what does it mean they didn't worship Him? אמר אלעזר אמר הקדוש
ברוך הוא אפילו כטורמוס הזה ששולקין אותו שבע פעמים ואוכלין אותו בקינוח
סעודה לא עשוני בני. Amar Elazar amar Hakadosh Baruch Hu afilu k'tormusa
hazeh shesholkin oto sheva pe'amim v'ochlin oto b'kinuach seuda lo asuni banai.
Even like this bean that you cook it seven
times and you just eat it for a
dessert, they didn't even treat me like this bean. Now what does
that mean? What's the idea? So רש״י Rashi indicates two different interpretations:
Who's the bean here? So one is that the Jewish people are
the bean, because for every time that they worshiped the foreign gods,
God punished them. So it's like they were punished seven times because
they worshiped seven foreign gods like the bean that was cooked seven
times. And the lousy bean after being cooked seven times becomes edible;
you get cooked seven times and you still abandon God and you
get suffering and you still abandon. The other interpretation, it sounds a
little bit more like God is the bean. So what does that
mean? So the מהרש״א Maharsha says it means because the bean you
eat as a dessert, and what God is saying is you not
only worshiped these other gods seven times, you didn't even have me
worship me together with the other gods. You completely abandoned me like
you didn't even have me for dessert. So that's a problem. Okay,
now תנא
משמיה דרבי מאיר מפני מה ניתנה תורה לישראל. Tana mishmei deRabbi Meir
mipnei mah nitna Torah l'Yisrael. Since we're talking about worshiping other gods
or whatever, anyway somehow this is loosely connected. Why was the תורה
Torah given to the Jewish people? Maybe we want to say something
nice about ישראל Yisrael rather than end on a negative note. מפני
מה ניתנה תורה לישראל מפני שהן עזים. Mipnei mah nitna Torah l'Yisrael
mipnei shehen azim. Because they are very hard and stubborn. So what
does it mean? So תנא דבי רבי ישמאל, Tana d'bei Rabbi Yishmael,
מימינו אש דת למו. Miyimino esh dat lamo. From God's right hand
was a fiery law for His people. אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא ראויין
הללו שתינתן להם דת אש. Amar Hakadosh Baruch Hu reuyin elu shetinaten
lahem dat esh. These people are so tough they can handle this
law of fire. איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, some say, דתיהם של אלו
אש. datehem shel elu esh. Their whole way, the way of the
people is this fiery way. What does that mean? שאילמלא ניתנה תורה
לישראל אין כל אומה ולשון יכולים לעמוד בפניהם. She-ilmalei nitna Torah l'Yisrael
ein kol uma v'lashon yecholim la'amod bifneihem. That you need the תורה
Torah to soften them up; they're so adamant and stiff-necked basically and
hard that if it weren't that the תורה Torah was given to
them, they would be destructive towards the other nations. So they need
the
תורה. Torah. So it seems like what it's sort of trying to
do is on the one hand saying like, okay, you know, we
whatever we sinned but like maybe I think what it's trying to
say is that like the, in a way, like, you know, the
what do you call it, the fact that we're עם קשי עורף
am keshei oref has very negative consequences, but it has positive consequences.
Because it means we're able to stick to, you know, our keeping,
you know, to, you know, we also, we also stick to, stick
to God and stick to the תורה Torah when we're not abandoning
God.
Yes, the תורה Torah essentially tames and controls the Jew because otherwise
the rest of humanity wouldn't be able to abide them. Abide the
Jews?
Yeah, I thought it meant more they would have been destructive to
the rest of humanity or something like that. Something like that. Right,
right. So anyway also maybe it works on them like the תורמוס,
turmus, like they've got to be cooked or something to be made
edible. תניא דאמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש Tanya de-amar Rabbi Shimon ben
Lakish ג' עזין הן, gimel azin hen, there's three that are very
tough. ישראל באומות, Yisrael be-umot, Jews amongst the
nations; כלב בחיות, kelev be-chayot, the dog, yeah, have to be like
wild dogs and wolves amongst the
animals;
תרנגול בעופות, tarnegol be-ofot, and right away the מהרש"א Maharsha points out
it's not like the dog is the bravest of the animals or
the strongest of the animals, but he's like the most
tenacious, the most annoying. Yeah, well maybe that. The chicken among birds;
ואית דאמרי אף עז בבהמה, ve-it de-amri af ez bi-vehemah, the ram
amongst the, amongst domesticated animals, דקא, daka, amongst the small animals; ואית
דאמרי אף צלף באילנות, ve-it de-amri af tzalaf be-ilanot, the צלף tzalaf
among trees; and רש"י doesn't exactly get what the point is of
that. Okay, we will have to end here for now.